A Guide to the Papers of Kevin Lynch,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Kevin Lynch
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13881
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Kevin Lynch, Charlottesville, Virginia, on April 26 and July 21, 2007.
Biographical/Historical Information
Kevin Lynch was born in Alexandria, Virginia, on June 5, 1962 and moved to Charlottesville in 1980 to attend the University of Virginia. Upon graduation from the University of Virginia as an electrical engineer in 1985 (BSEE), he worked for GE Fanuc until 1991 when he became an independent software contractor, specializing in embedded control systems. Lynch was elected to the Charlottesville City Council in 2000 and continued his work as a neighborhood activist. His activities include: Federation of Neighborhoods President (1998-1999); Martha Jefferson Neighborhood President (1996-1997); STAMP (Sensible Transportation Alternatives to the Meadow creek Parkway)-Founding Member; Book Buddies Program Tutor (1992-present). Currently he is serving on the following boards: Charlottesville-Albemarle Metropolitan Planning Organization of the Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission.
Scope and Content
The papers of Kevin Lynch consist of the papers and reports generated by Lynch's work on the Charlottesville City Council, ca. 1988-2007, ca. 1,500 items (6 boxes, 2.5 linear feet).
The collection consists chiefly of reports on issues before the City Council of Charlottesville, Virginia. Among those reports are: an environmental assessment of a local lumber yard and rail yard, 1993; a water demand analysis, 1997, and water supply report, 2004; market assessment for a convention/conference center, 1999, and tourism strategic plan, 2003; a master planning guide for Albemarle County development (neighborhood model), 1999; an historical report on several East Main Street buildings, 2000; a summary and evaluation of the Drug Court Program, 2000; an assessment of corrective measures for the Ivy Sanitary Landfill, 2001; Riverview Park report, 2001; site analyses for Cherry and Preston Avenues, 2002; a light-rail transit concept for Charlottesville and the County of Albemarle, 2002; summaries of the University of Virginia's capital plan, 2003, and Board of Visitors Building and Grounds Committee, 2004; a technical memorandum on Charlottesville traffic counts, 2003; overviews of the city mental health services, 2001, and foster care program, 2005;. and a survey of City Council election results, 1960-2004.
Also present are neighborhood projects status reports, 2004; a draft analysis of impediments to fair housing choices, 2004; an information technology strategic plan to support the business strategies of the city, a University of Virginia grounds area study, 2005; a downtown mall crossings feasibility study, 2005; 2006; police department report, 2006; an Urban Vision report, 2006; the annual report of the Charlottesville/Albemarle Commission on Children and Families, 2006; a report by the Charlottesville Community Forums on closing the local [minority student] achievement gap; an emergency medical service proposal, 2007; the Charlottesville transit service report, 2007; downtown designing guidelines of the Planning Commission's Board of Architectural Review, 2007; the school budget proposal, 2007-2008; the proposed Capital Improvement Program for 2008-2012.
In addition the collection contains memoranda, correspondence, and dockets and agendas pertaining to City Council meetings, as well as pertinent background material from other organizations. The collection also contains oversize site plans for the subdivision "Huntley" and for an apartment building on Jefferson Park Avenue.
Arrangement
The Kevin Lynch Papers are arranged alphabetically by topic following the general records of the Charlottesville City Council, such as agendas, minutes, etc. Topics include Charlottesville Education, Elections, Environment, Fiscal Year Budget, Neighborhoods, Planning, Real Estate, Social Services, Technology, Tourism, Transportation, and the University of Virginia.
Contents List
- Charlottesville City Council
  - Bills from Virginia General Assembly, 2007 April (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Charlottesville City Council Agendas, 2007 July (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Charlottesville City Council Agendas, 2007 May 21- June (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Charlottesville City Council Agendas, 2007 April-May 7 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Charlottesville City Council Agendas, 2007 January-March (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Charlottesville City Council Meeting Notices, 2007 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Charlottesville City Council Memos, Miscellaneous, 2007 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Charlottesville City Council Minutes, 2007 May-June (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Charlottesville City Council Minutes, 2006 December-2007 April (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Charlottesville City Council Vision, 2005-2007 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - City of Charlottesville Comprehensive Plan Public Hearing, 2007 June (Box-folder 1:11)
    (Chapters 1-9)
  - City of Charlottesville Comprehensive Plan Public Hearing, 2007 June (Box-folder 2:1)
    (Chapters 10-Glossary)
  - City of Charlottesville: Kevin Lynch's Council Notebook (A-G), 2005 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - City of Charlottesville: Kevin Lynch's Council Notebook (H-Q), 2005 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Community Involvement, Miscellaneous, 2006 September- 2007 June (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Kevin Lynch's Charlottesville City Council Notes, n.d. (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Newsletters- Miscellaneous, 2006 December-2007 April (Box-folder 2:7)
- Charlottesville Education
  - A Community Volunteer Tutorial That Works, 1996-1997 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Adult Education: Charlottesville City Schools, 2003 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - Charlottesville City Schools: 2007-08 School Budget Proposal, 2007 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Charlottesville City Schools: Capital Improvement Projects Committee Meeting, 2007 (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Charlottesville City Schools: Summary- Scholastic Assessment Test and Advanced Placement Program, 2004 - 2005 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Charlottesville City Schools: Suspension Center Intervention Program, n.d. (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Charlottesville Services for English Language Learners Program, 2005 - 2006 (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Closing the Local Achievement Gap, 2002-2006 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Computers 4 Kids Progress Report, 2002 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Early Literacy Screening in Kindergarten: Widespread Implementation in Virginia, 2005 (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Educating Poor Minority Children, 1988 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Families Learning Together: Johnson School, 2000 - 2001 (Box-folder 2:19)
  - Guidelines for Placing Students in the Alternative Education Program, n.d. (Box-folder 2:20)
  - Perspectives on the Charlottesville Schools Curriculum Management Audit, 2004 (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Preschool Education and Performance in Charlottesville, 2000-2002 (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Research Review Regarding SRA/ McGraw-Hill's Open Court Reading, n.d. (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Statistics: Charlottesville High School Graduates, 2004 (Box-folder 2:24)
  - The Impact of High Stakes Testing on Charlottesville City Schools, n.d. (Box-folder 2:25)
- Charlottesville Elections
  - City Council Election Results 1960-2004 and Voter Registration, 2004, 2007 (Box-folder 2:26)
- Charlottesville Environment
  - ABC's of Nuclear Power, 2007 (Box-folder 2:27)
  - Albemarle County and City of Charlottesville: Raw Water Supply Facility Permitting-Demand Analysis, 1997 (Box-folder 2:28)
  - Charlottesville City Council Work Session: Parks and Recreation, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Charlottesville Tree Packet, 2007 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - City of Bryan, Texas Calendar: Drinking Water Quality Report, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - City of Charlottesville Flood Plain Ordinance, 2007 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - City of Charlottesville: Gas Costs, Rates, and Purchasing Methods, 2007 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - City of Charlottesville: Riverview Park, 2001 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - City of Charlottesville: Holiday Trails Water Main, 2007 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - City of Charlottesville: Water Supply Status, 2004 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Ivy Sanitary Landfill: Assessment of Corrective Measures Addendum, 2001 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Proposed Conservation Districts' Standards, 2007 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Status of Environmental Investigations Related to Charlottesville Industrial Development Authority (CIDA) Projects, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 3:11)
- Charlottesville Fiscal Year Budget
  - City of Charlottesville: Fiscal Year 2007-2008 Budget Presentation, 2007 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - City of Charlottesville: Fiscal Year 2007-2008 Budget Proposals, 2006 - 2007 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - City of Charlottesville: Proposed Operating and Capital Budget, Fiscal Year 2006-2007, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - City of Charlottesville: Responses to City Council Budget Questions, 2007 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Fiscal Year 2007 Budget Work Plan, 2005 (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Fiscal Year Program and Agency Application and Funding Application, 2005-2006 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - House and Senate Approve Budget Conference Report, 2007 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Virginia Salary Survey, 2005-2006 (Box-folder 3:19)
- Charlottesville Neighborhoods
  - Analysis of Impediments to Fair Housing Choice, 2004 (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Back to the Future: The Need for Patient Equity in Real Estate Development Finance, 2007 (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Charlottesville City Council/ Planning Commission: Work Session- Neighborhoods, 2001 - 2005 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Charlottesville Department of Neighborhood Services: Staff Report, 2007 January - April (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Fair Housing: The Siting of Group Homes for the Disabled and Children, n.d. (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Fifeville Neighborhood Historic Survey, 2006 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Housing, Miscellaneous, 2007 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Huntley Amended Site Plan Architectural Drawings, 2006
  - Jefferson Park Avenue Apartment Buildings- Architectural Drawings, 2007
  - Neighborhood Development Services (NDS) Projects Completed, 2000-2004 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Proffers and Special Use Permit (SUP) Conditions/ Affordable Housing, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - The Neighborhood Model- Planning Liveable Albemarle Neighborhoods, 1999 (Box-folder 4:8)
- Charlottesville Planning
  - Charlottesville-Albemarle Metropolitan Planning Organization of the Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission: Agendas, 2007 April-June (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Charlottesville-Albemarle Metropolitan Planning Organization of the Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission: Agendas 2007 January - April (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Charlottesville-Albemarle Metropolitan Planning Organization: Fiscal Year 2007-2008 Work Program, 2007 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Charlottesville-Albemarle Metropolitan Planning Organization: Miscellaneous, 2006 - 2007 (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Charlottesville-Albemarle Metropolitan Planning Organization: Public Participation Policy, 2005 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - City of Charlottesville: Construction Communiqué, 2007 May-June (Box-folder 4:14)
  - City of Charlottesville: Construction Communiqué, 2007 February-April (Box-folder 4:15)
  - City of Charlottesville: Land Use and Implementation Chapters, 2007 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - City of Charlottesville Planning Commission- Height/Step backs for Discussion, 2007 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - City of Charlottesville Planning Commission Regular Docket, 2007 July (Box-folder 5:2)
  - City of Charlottesville Planning Commission Regular Docket, 2007 June (Box-folder 5:3)
  - City of Charlottesville Planning Commission Regular Docket, 2007 May (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Planning Commission- Zoning Ordinances for the City of Charlottesville, 2005-2007 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Six Things I Wish I Had Known When I First Became a Planning Commissioner, 2006 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission: Summary of Activities, 2007 (Box-folder 5:7)
- Charlottesville Real Estate
  - Cherry Avenue- Site Analysis, 2002 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - City of Charlottesville: 4th Street Mall Crossing Public Hearing, 2005-2007 (Box-folder 5:9)
  - City of Charlottesville Building Project Status, 2006-2007 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - City of Charlottesville: Community Development Block Grant (CDBG), n.d. (Box-folder 5:11)
  - City of Charlottesville: Downtown Design Guidelines, 2007 (Box-folder 5:12)
  - City of Charlottesville: Urban Vision Update, 2006 (Box-folder 5:13)
  - Feasibility Study: Downtown Mall Crossing 4th and 5th Streets, 2005 (Box-folder 5:14)
  - Preston Avenue-Site Analysis, 2002 (Box-folder 5:15)
  - Proposed Real Property Tax Increase, 2007 (Box-folder 5:16)
  - Structural Condition and Economic Feasibility Assessment for 101, 105, 107, and 111 East Main Street Buildings: Charlottesville, 2000 (Box-folder 5:17)
- Charlottesville Social Services
  - Charlottesville Commission on Children and Families (CCF): Annual Report, 2006 (Box-folder 5:18)
  - Charlottesville Commission on Children and Families (CCF) Key Findings, 2004 (Box-folder 5:19)
  - Charlottesville Department of Social Services: Foster Care, 2005-2007 (Box-folder 5:20)
  - Charlottesville Fire Department (CFD) Career Ambulance Proposal Executive Summary, 2006 (Box-folder 5:21)
  - Charlottesville Police Department: Year End Report, 2006 (Box-folder 5:22)
  - Charlottesville Weed and Seed Network Proposal Guidelines, 2003 (Box-folder 5:23)
  - Commission on Children and Families (CCF): Report on Focus Areas for Children and Families and 2004 Key Findings, 2004 (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Piedmont Workforce Network Proposal, 2006 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Region Ten: Community Services Board, 2000- 2001 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Three Year Summary and Evaluation of the Charlottesville/Albemarle Drug Court Problem, 1997 - 2000 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Workforce, Miscellaneous, 2007 (Box-folder 6:5)
- Charlottesville Technology
  - City of Charlottesville: 800 MHz Radio System, 2001 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - City of Charlottesville: Information Technology Strategic Plan, 2006 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - City of Charlottesville: Technology Plan Updates, 2000 - 2001 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Web Site Proposal for City of Charlottesville by Helix Computer Systems, Inc., 2000 (Box-folder 6:9)
- Charlottesville Tourism
  - Charlottesville Lead Team Retreat- How to Make Our Community Go from Good to Great, 2007 (Box-folder 6:10)
  - Charlottesville Regional Tourism Council: Market Assessment Regarding a Proposed Convention/ Conference Center, 1999 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Charlottesville Visitor Bureau: Proposal for Tourism Corporation, 2003 (Box-folder 6:12)
  - National Trust Names Charlottesville One of America's Dozen Distinctive Destinations, 2007 (Box-folder 6:13)
  - Watercolor Posters, n.d.
- Charlottesville Transportation
  - Albemarle Place, Cedar Hill Entrance Dispute, 2005 (Box-folder 6:14)
  - Charlottesville Street Deterioration Report, n.d. (Box-folder 6:15)
  - City of Charlottesville Jaunt Stockholders' Meeting, 2007 (Box-folder 6:16)
  - City of Charlottesville: Route 250 Bypass Interchange at McIntire Road, 2006 (Box-folder 6:17)
  - City of Charlottesville Traffic Counts, 2003 (Box-folder 6:18)
  - City of Charlottesville Transportation Chapter of Comprehensive Plan, 2007 (Box-folder 6:19)
  - Commonwealth Transportation Board: TransDominion Express Study Update, 2007 (Box-folder 6:20)
  - Corridor Concepts for Light-Rail Transit in Charlottesville and Environs, 2002 (Box-folder 6:21)
  - Virginia Transportation Funding Reports, 2007 (Box-folder 6:22)
- University of Virginia
  - University of Virginia: Area Plans, 2005 (Box-folder 6:23)
  - University of Virginia: Capital Plan, 2003 (Box-folder 6:24)
  - University of Virginia: Development Plans- Buildings and Grounds, 2004 (Box-folder 6:25)
  - University of Virginia: South Lawn Project, 2007 (Box-folder 6:26)